A Guide to the Independent Order of St. Luke Records, 1927-1945
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Independent Order of St. Luke Records, 1927-1945
The Library of Virginia
50950
.80 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Independent Order of St. Luke
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Ryan K. Smith
Biographical Information
The Independent Order of St. Luke was established in Baltimore, Maryland in 1867 by Mary Prout, a formerly enslaved woman, in order to provide members with life, disability, and burial insurance. The Order also provided members with mortgages and educational loans, championed numerous humanitarian causes, and served as a social organization for its members. The Order nearly became defunct under the leadership of William Forrest, and was revitalized in 1899 when Maggie L. Walker became head of the organization, a position she held until her death in 1934. Under the leadership of Walker, the Order established the Juvenile Department and expanded membership to over 100,000 members in 24 states. Though members of the Order included both men and women, the Order largely focused on the needs of its female members. After Walker's death, the Order continued to serve the Richmond community, and was formally disbanded in the 1980's.
Scope and Content
Records, 1927-1945, of the Independent Order of St. Luke include applications, benefit certificates, and death records of members of the organization's Juvenile Department. Applications detail the name, date of birth, age, and address of the applicant, as well as name of beneficiary and their relationship to the applicant. Applications also include the amount of required monthly dues, as well as the amount of term life insurance. Benefit certificates include the number and amount of the insurance policy, the name and assigned "Juvenile Circle" of the newly insured, as well the terms and conditions of the insurance policy. Death records include the name of deceased, as well as the location and date of their death. Collection also includes death claim receipts, which detail the amount and date of payments to beneficiaries, as well as some correspondence. Correspondence includes that of beneficiaries to the Office of the Juvenile Department of the Order of St. Luke, as well as some internal correspondence between employees. Several letters are addressed to Maggie L. Walker. Collection also contains notecards that detail the name, age, council number, certificate and claim number, and cause of death of adult members of the organization.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to the original order.
Contents List
- Virginia Harris, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Frederick Marshall, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Helen Thomas, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lucille Mickey, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Howard E. Cotton, 1927-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Lucile Sears, 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Samuel Hughes, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Helen E. Evans, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gladys M. Barrett, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Corrine Adams, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Maszie Merchant, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cornelia Powell, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Austin Barbor, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Fannie Mercer, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- James Diggs, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Alonzo Fairfax, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Catherine Solomon, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Mary Wilkerson, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Clarence Jones, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Charlie Lewis, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Celestine Mitchell, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Vernon Clark, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Norman Allen, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Earl Hinton, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- William Smith, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- James Mason, Jr., 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Mary Dillahunt, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Rebecca Pauline, 1935-1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Susie Dillard, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Virginia Scott, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Marshall C. Jones, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Geneive Johnson, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Alonzo A. Joyner, 1929-1943 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Mabel C. Johnson, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Benjamin L. Jones, 1933-1943 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Elizabeth Logan, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Corrine Elizabeth Williams, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Thomas Pettway, 1931-1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Joseph Grant, Jr., 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Henry Johnson, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Hattie Broader, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Crystal Johnson, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Catherine Travis, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Mollie Berger, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Sally L. Dillegaird, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Joe L. Harris (Brown?), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Mary E. Richardson, 1938-1945 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Barbara Brummel, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Paul L. Holland, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Sandra J. Wilson, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Frances Wars, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Forster Low, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Mattieline Gayles, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Sallie Smith, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Insurance Policy Notecards, 1927-1945 (Box 2)